Hello everyone, the title of this presentation is "TCLNet: Learning to Locate Typhoon Center Using Deep Neural Network".
And my name is Chao Tan, from Chongqing University of Technology.
The task of typhoon center location plays an important role in typhoon analysis.
In this work, we use a single frame infrared satellite cloud imagery to determine the position of typhoon eye or spin center.
The applications of typhoon center location are wide ranging.
For example, typhoon intensity estimation, typhoon path forecasting and typhoon center tracking.
In this work, we try to use a deep learning network to solve this problem.
Therefore, we first propose a brand-new large-scale typhoon center location dataset named TCLD,
which contains more than 1800 training samples and 300 testing samples from meteorological satellite.
In addition, we use the mean location error (MLE) to measure the performance of the algorithm on the TCLD dataset.
MLE calculates the coordinate distance between the predicted typhoon center and the corresponding label.
We also reported the MLE of human experience on TCLD dataset, from this, we can see that compared with the eyed typhoon,
the center locating error of the non-eyed typhoon is greater.
The main components of our typhoon center location network TCLNet are ConvBlock and ResBlock.
The overall structure of TCLNet is a fully convolutional encoding-decoding network.
It contains a preprocessing part for feature preprocessing and encode-decode part for feature transformation.
In addition, TCLNet generated the typhoon center coordinate heatmaps and trained using mean square error.
In the testing phase, we obtained the final typhoon center position through the coordinate heatmap.
In terms of experimentation, we conduct experiments on ResNet, SimpleBaseline, Feature Pyramid Network (FPN), Cascaded Pyramid Network (CPN) and Hourglass Network.
It can be seen that compare with the current best method, our TCLNet achieves a 14.4% increase in accuracy
on the basis of a 92.7% reduction in model parameters.
In the process of training TCLNet,
we observed that the model has large differences in Mean Square Error values for different samples in the course of the experiments, and the loss distribution is long-tailed.
Due to the training dataset contains about thirty-five percent non-eyed typhoon samples, and these hard samples contribute a large loss value during the training process,
thus affect the model to optimize in the correct direction.
To solve this problem, we propose a new loss function TCL+ for the task of typhoon center location.
TCL+ loss suppress the loss of hard samples in the training process, and instead learning it through easy samples.
We compare the effects of mean square error loss and TCL+ loss,
and the result shows that training with our TCL+ loss can achieve better performance than traditional mean square error loss.
We also visualize some test results of TCLNet.
It can be seen that TCLNet achieves comparable results on eyed typhoon samples compare with manual labels,
and also outputs reasonable results on non-eyed typhoon samples.
Our TCLNet follows the lightweight and simplest model architecture and achieves the best performance with the smallest amount of network parameters.
To illustrate this point, we studied the impact of different components and network structures on typhoon center location task.
From the result of the experiment, we can see that the performance of the models with strategies such as using Hourglass network,
increasing the downsampling scales and using skip connection is not as good as our TCLNet.
Meanwhile, the complex network architecture further increases the amount of model parameters.
In addition, we have experimentally verified the performance of different model architecture related hyperparameters.
It ensure that a relatively lightweight network is used to obtain the best result of typhoon center location.
We also analyze the impact of different standard deviations used to generate the ground-truth heatmap on the training results.
Small standard deviation will lead to too steep probability value distribution of heatmap,
which results in performance degradation due to too strict restrictions on the output of the model.
Conversely, a too large standard deviation will increase the supervision error during the training process since the probability value distribution of heatmap is too flat.
We conduct experiments on TCLNet with standard deviations ranging from 5 to 30 in interval of 5,
and it can be seen that the best effect can be achieve when standard deviation is set to 15.
Well, that's all of my presentation, thank you for your watching.